TheChaosLegion
l want to shine on you,
and always like that dazzling sun.
l will defend you
from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
lf only our hearts could connect,
l could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't
see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind
to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time,
and l know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day,
l'll be there for you.
l hope l can watch over you
like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
What l think doesn't matter.
（バルサ）いいもなにも―
They lost their home because of me.
こっちの事情で
住みかを奪っちまったんだ
それに もう
十分 ほとぼりは冷めてるし―
Besides, the uproar has mostly died down,
so l don't think there will be any problems.
特に問題はないと思うけどね
You think? Well, l'm sure
Toya's going to be ecstatic.
（タンダ）
そうか トーヤも喜ぶと思うよ
にしても
いくら街っ子だからって―
Really... l know he's
a town boy and all...
あそこまで 村の生活に
なじめないとは思わなかったけどな
...but l never imagined that he'd have such
a hard time getting used to village life.
それに比べて チャグムは偉いな
Compared to him,
Chagum's done an admirable job.
Where's Toya now?
（バルサ）トーヤ 今 どこにいる？
（タンダ）うん？
家を探すって約束だから
これから会うけど
l promised that l'd find a place for him,
so we're supposed to meet up later.
That's perfect. Take us along with you.
（バルサ）ちょうどいいや
私らも連れてってくれ
頼みたいことがあるんだ
There's something l want
to ask him to do for me.
少々 荒療治が必要なんでね
Some drastic measures
are called for here.
Episode 10
Soil
and
Heroes
Drastic measures, huh?
（タンダ）荒療治ねえ
As far as l can tell, he seems
to be fitting in well enough.
俺には うまく なじんでるように
見えるけどなあ
チャグムは
引っ込み思案でもないし―
That's because Chagum isn't the
introverted type, and he's not timid.
臆病でもないからね
ただ賢すぎるんだ
The thing is, he's too
clever for his own good.
おまけに孤独に耐性があるから―
Also, since he was already
accustomed to isolation...
...he would never complain
even if he was feeling lonely.
寂しくったって
愚痴一つ こぼさない
But that's not going to help him
live his life here in town, will it?
でも それじゃ これから先―
ずっと街で暮らそうってわけには
いかないだろ？
本当の平民にならなきゃ
息が詰まっちまうよ
Unless he becomes a true commoner,
he'll always feel stifled.
You really think so?
そんなもんかねえ
ln that case, l guess the real issue is
whether Toya will make a good instructor.
となると問題は トーヤに
その指南役が務まるかどうかだな
（トーヤ）ねえさーん！
Balsa!
（トーヤ）ねえさん！ あっ…
本当に生きてる
You're really alive!
They said you were alive,
but you really are!
生きてるとは聞いてたけど
ホントに生きてたよ
いろいろ すまなかったね
Sorry about everything.
あんたには
ずいぶんと迷惑をかけた
l've put you through a lot of trouble.
l hope you can forgive me.
許しておくれ
Don't be like that... Just seeing you two
alive and well makes it all worth it.
そんなこと…
俺 ２人の元気な顔が見られれば
それで十分ですよ
What's Saya up to? ls she okay?
サヤは どうしてる？ 元気かい？
（トーヤ）ええ そりゃ もう
Sure, of course!
あいつは器用だから
どこでも うまく やっていけんです
She can master anything,
so she can get by anywhere.
村では よく働くってんで―
She's such a hard worker in the village
that they're bringing her marriage offers.
嫁に来てくれなんて話も
あるぐらいで
lsn't that right?
ねえ？
（タンダ）そうだね
l guess they are.
But you're coming back
to town anyway?
それでも やっぱり
こっちに戻ってくるのかい？
ええ ねえさんに もらった金も
まんま残ってますし
Yeah. We still have all the money that
you gave us, so l thought we'd...
ヘヘヘ
（バルサ）ふーん
それじゃ 早速だけど
仕事を頼んでもいいかい？
ln that case, l know you just got here,
but would you mind doing a job for me?
You mean it? Sure, just name it!
l'll do anything!
ホントっすか？
そりゃ もう なんなりと
実はね…
The thing is...
この子に 頼まれ屋の仕事を
教えてやってほしいんだ
...l want you to teach this boy
how to be an errand runner.
What do you say?
どうだい？
俺は いいですけど その…
l'm up for it, but...
Well...
lt'll be all right. l'll be watching nearby.
大丈夫 近くから私も見てるから
ln that case, l guess we'll be okay.
だったら 安心かな
Come on, you don't need to be
so tense. lt's not that hard a job.
あんまり緊張すんなって
そんな難しいことじゃないんだから
l don't know...
l just can't seem to get into it.
なんか 調子 出ないなあ
Hey, l've got it!
l just came up with a great idea.
そうだ いいこと考えた
From now on, let's pretend
that you're my little brother!
今から チャグムは
俺の弟分ってことにしよう
誰かに怪しまれたとき
いろいろ言い訳しなくて済むしさ
That way, if anybody gets suspicious, we
won't have to make up any lame excuses.
So from now on, call me "big brother."
だから
俺のことは“兄貴”って呼ぶんだ
Big brother?
兄貴？
（トーヤ）そう 兄貴だ
Yep. Big brother, that's me.
あれからいこう
Let's start with that.
Delicious hekimooms
fresh off the grill and piping hot!
Hekimooms?
（チャグム）ヘキムーム？
lt's a grilled candy that's a mixture of
egg whites, sugar, and pine nut flour.
卵白に 砂糖と松の実の粉を
混ぜて焼いた お菓子さ
扇(おうぎ)の下(しも)の子供たちは
みんな食ってる
They're a favorite of the kids
here in Ogi no Shimo.
Listen up.
いいか？ ここいらじゃ もっぱら
こいつらさえあれば事足りる
As long as you have these on you,
you can get anything you want around here.
A hundred of these han coins...
equals one lugal.
このハン硬貨100枚で１ルガル
覚えたか？
（チャグム）うん
Got that?
（トーヤ）よし じゃ
あの１袋40ハンのヘキムームを―
Okay, we're going to buy a
40-han bag of hekimooms...
...but just with these.
これだけで買うんだ
10ハン足りないけど
But that is 10 han short.
What can l get you?
（露天商）あー らっしゃい
１袋ください
（露天商）40ハンね
l'd like one bag, please.
That'll be 40 han.
高(たけ)えな
That's pretty steep.
lf you go to that stand over there,
you can get them for 30.
（トーヤ）
あっちの店なら30ハンで買えるよ
Really? Where is it?
本当？ それ どこですか？
（トーヤ）辻裏(つじうら)の出店だよ
The food stand in the alley over there.
じゃ 僕も そっちで
All right, then. l think l'll
buy mine over there too.
Hey...hold on a minute!
（露天商）おい ちょっと待ちな！
うちの 一口 食ってみな
ホントうめえから
Just give one of mine a try,
and you'll see! They're delicious!
でも やっぱり安いほうにします
Still... l think l'll go with
the cheaper ones after all.
（露天商）
あっ 待った 待った 待った！
Wait, wait, wait!
じゃ 特別に… 30で どうだ？
Okay, l'll give you a special discount
just this once! How about 30?
Worked like a charm, l see.
うまくいったみたいだな
こんなに あっさり
まけてくれるとは思わなかった
l did not believe that he
would lower the price so easily.
You need to learn how to do
what we just did all by yourself.
今やったことを 今度は
１人で やれるようになんなきゃな
Don't worry about it now.
For your first time, you did great!
心配すんな
最初にしちゃ上出来だよ
うまいだろ？
（チャグム）うん
Good, aren't they?
Now you're an official resident
of Ogi no Shimo.
これで チャグムも扇の下の住人だ
Huh? Where's...
あれ？ ねえさん…
まあ その辺にいるだろう
Well, l guess she's
around here someplace.
次 行くか
（チャグム）うん
Ready for your next lesson?
（テホイ）
声をからしてモン･ジン･ゼン
Mon Jin Zen...so exciting
you'll shout yourself hoarse!
さあ 皆々様 張った 張った！
Ladies and gentlemen,
place your bets!
（チャグム）あれは？
What is that?
（トーヤ）モン･ジン･ゼン
いわゆる賭け事ってやつだな
Mon Jin Zen. lt's what you'd call
a game of chance. Gambling.
lt's a game for grown-ups.
大人の遊びだよ
（チャグム）ふーん
待てよ
これも社会勉強ってことになるかも
Hey, wait a minute...
This might count as
social education too.
Come on, place your bets!
Who will bet a han?
（テホイ）
さあ！ 張ってちょうだい ハン硬貨
張ってください ルガルの銅貨
Who will bet a copper lugal?
Place your bet, and leave it to
the mercy of the gods!
あとは ひたすら神頼み
Mon Jin Zen...so exciting
you'll shout yourself hoarse!
声をからしてモン･ジン･ゼン
Ladies and gentlemen,
place your bets!
さあ 皆々様 張った 張った！
Mon!
（大工）モン！
（女性）ジン！
Jin!
あそこで
表が白い外国の硬貨を回すんだ
The man over there spins
foreign coins that have a white face.
それを全部で３つ回して―
He spins a total of three of them...
...and the object of the game is to bet
how many of them will come up heads.
そのうち何枚が表になって
止まるかを当てる遊びなんだ
１枚だったら“モン”
２枚だったら“ジン”
lf it's one, it's Mon.
lf it's two, that's Jin.
３枚とも白だったら
“ゼン”つって倍返し
lf all three come up white, that's Zen,
and you get back twice what you bet.
でも 逆に３枚とも黒だったら―
But if three blacks come up...
“総取り”つって親の勝ちだ
...that's called "house takes all"
and the house wins everything.
（テホイ）
さあ 最後の１枚が回っちまうよ！
All right, the final coin
is about to be spun!
Are there any other bets?
他 ないかい？
My, this young man is a big better!
おっ！ にいさん 気前がいいねえ
なんと
ゼンに最後 １ルガルが入った！
We have a last-minute bet on Zen!
A perfect place to close the betting!
The time for speculation is over!
きりがいいや
ここで予想は打ち切りだ
あとは 裏か表か神頼み
Whether it's heads or tails...
it's up to your prayers!
Pray that the coins
will come your way!
自分の目に
硬貨がそろうよう祈ってな！
こういうのは 実際やってみねえと
よく分かんないだろ？
Stuff like this doesn't really make sense
unless you try it for yourself.
さあ 来いよ ゼン！
Okay, let's see a Zen!
Yes! Yes!
Two whites! Jin!
（ジュロ）白２つ ジン！
かあーっ！
…と まあ こういう遊びだ
Anyway, that's how the game works...
Come on, place your bets!
Who will bet a han?
（テホイ）
さあ！ 張ってちょうだい ハン硬貨
張ってください ルガルの銅貨
Who will bet a copper lugal?
ln this game, does one have to bet
before the third coin is spun?
あれって ３枚目を投じる前に
賭けなくちゃいけないの？
いや 初めの１枚が倒れるまでなら
賭けられるけど―
No, you're allowed to place your bet
until the first coin lands...
そんな のんきにしてたら
気合いが入らないだろ？
...but it's not as exciting
if you wait that long, you know?
You gotta be ready to bet
before he spins the first coin.
投げ手が１枚目を放る前から―
賭けるくらいでなくっちゃ
勝てるものも勝てねえよ
Otherwise, you're never gonna win.
ああ… 俺ってホント バカ
Oh, l'm such a moron!
Do you know how many lunches l could've
bought from Nogi's with that lugal?
１ルガルありゃ ノギ屋の弁当が
どれだけ食えんだよ
ちくしょう！ 取り返してえ！
Crap! l wanna get it back!
負けてよかったんだよ
You were better off losing.
なんで？
勝つほうがいいに決まってるだろ
What're you talking about?
Winning is always better!
That is true enough,
but you could not have won.
それは そうだろうけど
勝つのは無理だよ
lt seemed like the coin spinner could make
the coins come up any way he wanted.
だって あの硬貨を回す人
出したい目が出せるみたいだから
Come on, how could he
possibly do that?
そんなこと できるわけないだろ
Wait, how could you possibly know that the
first time you saw the game being played?
…って なんで １回 見たくらいで
そんなこと分かるんだよ？
分かんないけど 分かるよ
l do not know how l know.
l just know.
ホントか？
（チャグム）うん
Are you serious?
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
白１つ モン！
One white! Mon!
本当だ
（チャグム）でしょ？
Wow, you're right!
See? lf this goes on, these people
will lose all of their money.
このままいけば―
この人たちは 持っている お金を
全額 取られることになる
Do you see that large carpenter
sitting there?
あそこに
体の大きな大工さんいるよね？
He will most likely lose
in the next round as well.
あの人は多分 次も負けるよ
あそこの おばあさんは
今は勝ってるけど―
The old woman over there is
winning for the time being...
多分 次に狙われる
...but l suspect that she
will be their next target.
What makes you say that?
なんでだ？
１ルガル以上 賭けるからだよ
Because she will bet
more than one lugal.
M-More than one...
ハン硬貨だと 負けても
案外 負けたという意識を持たない
M-More than one...
When one bets using han coins...
...losing does not seem so bad.
But anyone who loses a lugal would
definitely want to win it back, right?
だけど １ルガル負けた人は
絶対に取り戻そうと考えるでしょ？
そのとおり
That's for sure...
でも １ルガルを取り戻すためには
10ハンなら10回―
But to win back one lugal, one would
have to win ten bets of 10 han.
50ハンでも ２回 勝たなきゃ
１ルガル取り戻せないよね
Even betting 50 han, one would still have
to win twice to recover that lugal, see?
（チャグム）そう考えると 勝率が
８分の３のモンやジンより―
With that in mind, the impulse is not to
bet on Mon or Jin, whose odds are 3-in-8...
８分の１ながら倍返しの
ゼンに賭けたくなるのが人情でしょ
...but rather to bet on Zen's
double return in spite of its 1-in-8 odds.
でも あの人は
最後の一投で出目を操って―
But that person is manipulating
the outcome of the final throw...
...making it so that they
make a profit in the end.
最終的に 自分たちが
もうかるようにしているんだ
誰も賭けていないときに
よくゼンが出るのも そのせいだよ
That is also why Zen comes up
so often when no one has bet on it.
H-Hey, wait just a minute!
ちょちょちょ…
ちょっと待ってくれ
lf they can really do that, wouldn't that
make this... a rigged game?
本当に そんなことができたら
それって…
いかさまじゃねえか？
でも あの人たちだって
商売だから しかたがないよ
But for those men, it is also their livelihood,
so it can't really be helped.
そりゃそうだけど…
Well, no, but...
Also, the majority of the people here
seem to be enjoying the gambling.
それに ここにいる人たちの大半は
駆け引きを楽しんでいるんでしょ？
lf one's objective were to earn money,
it would be insanity to play such games.
お金を稼ぐことが目的なら―
こんな遊びに興じるのは
酔狂に過ぎるよ
一人ひとりだと―
lt is difficult to spot individually because
of the difference in their wins and losses.
勝敗がバラバラだから
分かりにくいけど―
親対子で見たら 仮に
インチキをしていなくても―
But seen as a house-versus-player game,
even if the house does not cheat...
...the odds are so heavily stacked against
these people that they cannot win.
あの人たちには―
確率的に 勝つことが
できないようになっているんだ
えっ？
（女性）ああ… 負けた
Goodness, l lost.
lf you'd kept winning, we would've been
driven out of business by one little old lady.
これ以上 勝たれたら―
ばあさん１人に
潰されちまうところだった
まだ 運は こっちにあるな
Looks like luck is still on our side.
（女性）次は 絶対 勝ってやる！
l'll win for sure next time, just you wait!
Come on, place your bets!
（テホイ）さあ！ 張ってちょうだい…
言ってくる
（チャグム）えっ？
l'm going over there.
納得できない
l can't let this go.
Who do you think you are,
you big, fat cheat?
やいやい！ この いかさま野郎！
（トーヤ）汚(きたね)えじゃねえか
正々堂々 勝負しろ！
You're playing dirty!
Run the game fair and square!
しょうがないねえ
What are we going to do with that boy?
You're slandering our good name.
人聞きが悪いな
l can understand that you're angry
because you lost all your money...
有り金 取られて
頭にきてるのは分かるが―
金のないヤツは とっとと帰んな
...but if you're penniless,
you'd better leave.
（トーヤ）あいたっ！
Yeah, beat it!
（大工）そうだ すっこんでろ！
ダメだ 行こう
lt's no use. Let's go.
せめて みんなが
金を巻き上げられるのを―
l hoped that l could at least
keep them from losing all their money...
止めようと思ったけど―
俺には無理だ
...but l guess it's beyond me.
ちょっと待って
Wait a moment.
トーヤは 自分のお金を
取り返したかったんじゃないの？
l thought that you wanted to
recover your money, Toya.
l played with fire, and l got burned.
あれは自業自得
もういいよ 行こう
lt's okay. Let's go.
止めよう！
Let's stop them.
lf you want to help these people,
l will do it for you.
トーヤが
みんなを助けたいなら―
俺が代わりに行ってくる
お… おい チャグム！
Hey! Chagum!
This is exactly why commoners
are looked down upon as fools.
（チャグム）これだから
民草はバカだというんだ
あらかじめ
負けると決まった勝負を―
They delude themselves
into thinking that a game is fair...
...even when that game
is rigged against them.
対等の駆け引きだと
思い込んでいるんだからね
まったく おめでたいよ
Truly, what a bunch of fools!
Do you not see?
分からないかな？
This man can make the coins
come up whichever way he wants.
この人は 出したい目が出せるんだ
lf you continue playing,
you will be the first to lose.
このままいけば
まず あなたが最初に負けますよ
Then you will lose, ma'am.
And then you, miss.
その次は おばあさん
その次は おねえさん
みんなは
今は勝たせてもらってるだけ
They are simply letting you
win for the time being.
あっという間に一文無しになる
But before you know it,
your pockets will be empty.
こんな簡単なことが見抜けないから
あんたたちは みんな―
You cannot see through such
a simple scam, and that is why...
...you will always remain
the ignorant masses.
いつまでたっても愚民なんだ
何なんだ？ このガキは
Who does this kid think he is?
まったくだよ
偉そうなこと言うんじゃないよ
Honestly! Don't talk like
you know everything, boy.
He's just jealous of us. lt's because
his big brother lost his money.
（女性）やっかんでんのさ
自分の兄貴が負けたもんだから
You better hurry home, boy.
（すし職人）
おい 坊主 早(はえ)えとこ うち帰(けえ)んな
おっかさんに しぼられっぞ
Or you'll get into trouble
with your mama.
…って 俺か？
（笑い声）
Wait, that's me!
坊主 勇気があるな
You have guts, little man.
Seeing as how you're so sure
of what you say...
それだけ自信満々に
言うからには―
こいつが出目を出せるってこと
証明できるんだろうな？
...l assume you can prove that this man
can control what side comes up?
Balsa...
ねえさん…
いいよ 証明してみせる
Very well. l shall prove it to you.
何言ってんだよ
そんなの無理に決まってんだろ
What are you saying?
You can't prove it!
ねえさんも いないんだぞ 帰ろう
Balsa isn't around, either!
C'mon, let's go!
lt is all right. Leave this to me.
大丈夫 任せてよ
いいかい？ 兄貴
（トーヤ）お… おう！
You ready, big brother?
Y-Yeah!
One white... Mon.
白１つ モン
l have won the argument, l take it?
これで俺の勝ちですよね
まあ １回ではな
That was just one round.
（大工）ちょっと待った
Wait a minute.
l'll bet for the boy.
坊主の代わりに俺が賭ける
いいだろ？
That okay with you?
There it is! A double return!
来た！ 倍返し！
（トーヤ）やったー！
There it is! A double return!
We did it!
（男性）どういうこと？
（男性）出目が読めるのか？
He can tell how they'll land?
続けろ
Keep playing.
私もやるよ
l want in too!
We should bet on Jin, right?
ジンに賭ければいいんだな？
（チャグム）いえ ダメです
No. That will not work.
Do not bet on anything.
何も賭けないで
（女性）どういうことよ？
What do you mean?
No one can win this round.
次に来る目は 誰も勝てない
Three black! House takes all!
（トーヤ）黒３つ 親の総取り
最後 賭けなくて正解だったな
Not betting on the last one
was a smart move.
Yes, but the money you bet
on the first throws is...
でも 最初に賭けた分が…
That's all right. You have to tell us.
How do you know?
それはいい それより教えてくれ
どうして分かるんだ？
知りたいね 教えとくれ
l'm dying to know! Please, tell me!
（チャグム）あの人は３枚目で―
This man can control the outcome of
the first two coins using the third coin.
２枚目と１枚目の出目を
操ることができるんです
When he throws the third coin...
それは ３枚目を投げるとき―
...one can tell the outcome
by looking at this man's hand.
あのおじさんの手を見れば
分かります
When he grips his sash with
the thumb on top, it signals Mon.
親指を上にして
帯の端をつかんでいる場合はモン
When he grips it with the thumb
tucked into the sash, that signals Jin.
親指を帯に入れている場合はジン
帯をつかまず
拳を握っている場合は―
When he clenches his fist, that is
the signal for the roller to produce Zen.
ゼンの目が出ます
（すし職人）
なるほど そいつは いただけねえな
Now l get it... That's unacceptable.
Here in Yogo,
we call that a fixed game.
ヨゴじゃ そいつは
“いかさま”っつうんだぜ
（男性１）そうだ そうだ！
（男性２）金 返せ！
l want my money back!
What are you trying to pull?
（男性３）ふざけんじゃねえよ！
（男性４）この いかさま野郎！
You damned con artists!
あなたも商売でやっていることは
分かります
l do understand that you
are running a business here.
But these people are
enjoying your game.
でも みんな
この遊びを楽しんでいるんだ
次からは―
From now on, please run your games
according to official guidelines.
役所(やくどころ)の認めた やり方で
賭場を立ててくださいね
なっ？ 兄貴
（トーヤ）そのとおりよ
Right, big brother?
Yeah, that's right.
（テホイ）待ちな
Wait a minute.
How about a one-on-one match?
１対１で勝負しねえか？
ここまでやられたら
二度と ここいらには顔は出せねえ
After what you've done, we can't
show our faces around here again.
だから いかさまなしの一点勝負
So let's play an
all-or-nothing round with no tricks.
l'll throw the coins myself.
俺が硬貨を投げる
もし お前が勝てば―
lf you win, l'll return all of the money
that we got from these people today.
今日 巻き上げた分
ここにいる客に 全額返そう
But if l win, l walk away with
that necklace of yours.
ただし俺が勝った場合
お前の その首飾りをもらう
ダメだ… それだけはダメだ
そいつは おっかさんの…
No, don't do it!
You can't bet the necklace!
You got that from your...
やるよ
l accept.
いくぞ
Here we go.
He won! He won!
やったー！
That was awesome!
He did it, he did it!
ハァ…
（トーヤ）やった やった！
He did it!
H-Hey, l'm not the one
you should be picking up!
俺じゃねえっての！
C'mon, brother! Wait for me!
兄貴！ ちょっと待って！
兄貴！
Big brother!
You're the big brother, you fool!
バカ野郎 お前(めえ)が兄貴だろうが！
Hey! Come on, mister! Put me down!
（トーヤ）
ちょっと おじさん 降ろして！
痛い痛い痛い！
Well, that was a surprise...
l thought l was waking a sleeping child...
（バルサ）驚いたね
寝た子を起こそうとして―
...but l might have aroused something
more formidable than l thought.
えらいもんを
起こしちまったかもしれないよ
As l sat huddled and alone, holding
back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like l was about
to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were,
at my side before l knew it.
lt was none other than you
who was there for me.
l keep wishing, "l want to be strong."
l stumble and hurt myself again.
But because l have you to believe in,
l can get back to my feet.
l simply want to tell
my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs,
again and again.
l call out to my precious loved one.
ls my voice reaching you?
ln this world that always changes,
human warmth never does.
l'm certain l sensed the presence
of the one that l hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
Toya has disappeared.
Saya has lost consciousness.
And then Tanda...
Next time, "Flower Wine for Tanda."
Episode 11
Flower Wine for Tanda
May my prayers reach the border
between Nayug and Sagu.